Good morning.
Good morning. I'm Dan Nargiz and I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer
while he is not here. Today's July 18th, it is the 12th
of תמוז, Tammuz, and today's דף daf is מח. mem chet. We're
starting on the fourth line of מח mem chet עמוד א. amud
aleph. My colleague, did you have a question already? We didn't start.
Okay.
So we start from the גמרא gemara says תא שמע tashma at
the end of the fourth line on the top of מח mem
chet עמוד א. amud aleph. So we're going to have a case
which is similar to some of the cases in the previous משנה.
mishnah. We're going to have a case about which gets into some
tangential topics about צניעות tzniut a little bit, which is interesting. And
then we're gonna have a number of cases from רבא Rava that
are similar to the case in the משנה mishnah and we'll see
how far we get. So תא שמע. tashma. הכניס שורו לחצר בעל
הבית שלא ברשות. Hechnish shoro l'chatzer ba'al habayit shelo birishut. You brought,
so someone brought his animal into the property of someone else without
permission. ובא שור ממקום אחר, Uba shor mimakom acher, a third party's
שור shor enters into the property ונגחו, unagcho, פטור. patur. So someone
is going to be פטור patur from the damages in this case.
We're going to have to see, is it going to be the
person who owns the second שור shor or is it going to
be the owner of the חצר? chatzer?
Because the whole, if someone is פטור, patur, someone else is חייב?
chayav? Is that what you're saying?
Well, we're going to have to see, it says it's an unclear
ברייתא. braita. ואם הכניס ברשות, Ve'im hechnish birishut, חייב. chayav. If you
brought it in with permission, then he, unclear who the he is,
חייב. chayav. So מאן פטור מאן חייב? man patur man chayav? So
who's the one who's going to be פטור patur and who's the
one who's going to be חייב? chayav? לאו פטור בעל החצר וחייב
בעל החצר? lav patur ba'al hachatzer vechayav ba'al hachatzer? Are we really
saying that the בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer is going to be פטור
patur if he did not give permission, but if he gave permission
to bring the animal in, then he's going to be responsible to
the first party, the fact that the third party caused the damage?
He didn't do anything. What, just because he wasn't watching it carefully
enough? I mean, we're seeing here that the owner of the property
has a certain amount of שמירה, shemira, but that seems a little
bit extreme. לא, lo, פטור בעל השור וחייב בעל השור. patur ba'al
hashor vechayav ba'al hashor. No, the third party who owns the second
animal who caused the damage is the one who's going to be
either פטור patur or חייב. chayav. So we'll have to see. אי
הכי i hachi מאן ברשות? man birishut? So what does it matter
then that it was with the permission of the owner of the
חצר? chatzer? Because the third party obviously didn't have permission at all.
So why does it matter whether the first party got permission either
way? מאי שלא ברשות? mai shelo birishut? איכא דאמרי ika amri הא
מני רבי טרפון היא. ha mani Rabbi Tarfon hi. It must be
according to רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon position we saw already. רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon is of the opinion דאמר משונה קרן בחצר הניזק נזק
שלם משלם. d'amar meshuneh keren bechatzer hanizak nezek shalem meshalem. So what
does רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon say? רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says even
though שור תם shor tam normally pays חצי נזק, chatzi nezek, even
a שור תם shor tam according to רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, if
it's in רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, if it's in private property,
pays נזק שלם, nezek shalem, full damages. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon thinks
חצי נזק chatzi nezek for a שור תם shor tam is only
in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. And therefore the fact that whether there
was רשות reshut or not, that is whether there was permission or
not for this person to bring his animal in, is what makes
it whether it was deemed to be חצר הניזק chatzer hanizak or
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Whether it was private property or public property.
That is, it's not actually whether it's private or public property, but
the fact of granting רשות reshut to bring your animal in makes
it more of a public property. And thus it would be a
case of פטור, patur, that is the owner of the שור shor
is פטור patur from paying נזק שלם, nezek shalem, but would still
pay חצי נזק. chatzi nezek.
That's not what it sounded like at all. That's not what it
sounded like at all.
That's the first attempt at understanding this ברייתא. braita. That is, this
is all according to רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and the fact of
granting רשות reshut or not makes it whether it's רשות הרבים reshut
harabim where you only pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek or if it's
חצר הניזק chatzer hanizak where you would pay נזק שלם. nezek shalem.
But you should have said חייב חצי נזק.
chayav chatzi nezek. Exactly. So okay.
Yeah, this is not exactly, technically, חצר הניזק chatzer hanizak should be
the חצר chatzer of the person who suffered the damage.
That's a very good point. It's not actually in a technical sense
חצר הניזק chatzer hanizak because it does not belong to the owner
of the animal, except that
the
owner of the animal was given permission to bring his animal in.
So to some extent that is considered a granting of ownership. We
saw already the fact that the right to put your fruit out
in someone else's property is also a sort of קניין kinyan in
the property itself. It's fruit. It's almost becomes a שותפות. shutafut. Now
you're going to have to ask another question. It is many levels.
The other question we saw is already there was a מחלוקת machloket
previously in the second פרק perek I think, about חצר השותפים chatzer
hashutfim where there was damage caused. But the ראשונים rishonim note the
difference between חצר השותפים chatzer hashutfim where one partner damages the other,
this is a third party damaging something in חצר השותפים. chatzer hashutfim.
So I'm guessing the guy who suffered the damage in this case
did not have permission to be inside this
חצר. chatzer. In the רישא. reisha.
Correct, he did not have permission to bring his animal in. Therefore
it functions like a, like רשות הרבים reshut harabim for his purposes.
That is, it's not his property.
Levi, the third party. Okay, so
בראשות הוי ליה כקרן בחצר הניזק ומשלם נזק שלם, שלא בראשות הוי
ליה כקרן ברשות הרבים ולא משלם אלא חצי נזק. Berishus havei lei
kekeren bechatzer hanizak umishalem nezek shalem, shelo berishus havei lei kekeren birshus
harabbim velo mishalem ela chatzi nezek. That's just saying what we already
said, that is, which case—so Rabbi Tarfon's שיטה. shitta. Now, again, remember
he has to say Rabbi Tarfon was rejected. So the fact that
this ברייתא braisa must be interpreted according to Rabbi Tarfon's שיטה shitta
is a little bit difficult, but that's the only way it seems
to make sense of it because the first part is taking the
level of שמירה shmira necessary from the owner of the property to
a full extreme, that is, who's responsible if someone breaks into my
property and kills someone else's animal? Oh, it was my fault because
I didn't guard the animal well enough. Well, that would be absurd.
Okay.
I'm sorry, so—so what would the חכמים Chachamim say in this case
then?
So the—the everyone who disagrees with Rabbi Tarfon, who says that you
don't pay נזק שלם nezek shalem for שור תם shor tam even
in חצר הניזק, chatzer hanizak, then all we're talking about here is
the fact that you would always pay—you would always pay חצי נזק
chatzi nezek even in רשות הניזק, reshus hanizak, and then there would
be no difference between the two cases of whether there was רשות
reshus or not. Then they would both be cases where you would
pay חצי נזק, chatzi nezek, where the owner of the שור—of shor
the goring שור—would shor pay חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. So according to
רבנן, Rabbanan, there would be no difference between whether there was permission
or not, and then it would make no sense to distinguish between
them. So it must
be
Rabbi Tarfon, which is in a totally different sphere. Okay. ההיא איתתא
דעלתה למיפא בההוא ביתא. Hahi itteta de'alata lemifa behahu beita. A certain
woman went up to a house to bake there, okay?
אתא ברחא דמרי דביתא אכלה ללישא. Ata barcha demari debeita achala lelisha.
The goat of the owner of the house came and ate her
dough, חביל ומית, Chavil umit, he got damaged and—and he died. So
the goat—the owner of the house's goat—ate the woman's dough and the
goat died because it overate. We saw this already, the question of
animals overeating. So חייבת, Chayaves, she's—she's liable for the death of the
goat.
So—sorry—חייבה רבא לשלומי דמי ברחא. Chiyava Rava leshalumei dmei barcha. So Rava
made her pay for the price of the goat.
So לימא פליגי אדרב, Leima pligi adeRav, maybe Rava disagrees with Rav,
דאמר רב, de'amar Rav, why? Because Rav had said, הויא לה שלא
תאכל, Havaya lah shelo tochal, it's up to the animal's
best—the animal has its own sense of when it should stop eating,
and if it overeats to the point that it's going to die,
that's the animal's fault; it's not the person's fault for having left
the food out. So הויא לה שלא תאכל. Havaya lah shelo tochal.
So אמרי הכא השתא התם שלא ברשות. Amri hacha hashta hatam shelo
berishus. No, it must have been in that case it was without
permission. לא קיבלה עליה נטירותא. Lo kibla aleiah netiruta. And—and therefore the
person who came into the house did not accept upon her—or himself—responsibility
for the property of the homeowner. הכא ברשות, Hacha berishus, in this
case where it was with permission that she came to bake her
bread, so קיבלה עליה נטירותא, kibla aleiah netiruta, she accepted upon herself
a certain level of שמירה shmira over the animal while it was
in the house.
But it makes no sense. If she trespasses, she gets off easier
than if she gets there by permission?
So let's see. If you're trespassing, you've accepted no responsibility over the
property of the homeowner. So if the homeowner's goat comes and does
something to my property, comes and eats my dough, well, then it's—it's
his fault. It was the goat's fault.
But he doesn't have to pay you for your dough.
I come to do some work in your kitchen and then your
oven burnt—lights on fire and burns down. To a certain extent, you
could say that makes sense, that that's my fault because even though
it's your property, the fact that you allowed me to come in
means I have accepted responsibility for what damages take place while I'm
there. Now we're going to have to see there's going to be
a stipulation. מאי שנא מהא אשה שנכנסה לטחון חטין אצל בעל הבית
שלא ברשות ואכלתן בהמתו של בעל הבית פטור. Mai shna meha ishah
shenichnesah litchon chitin etzel ba'al habayis shelo berishus ve'achaltan behemato shel ba'al
habayis patur. How is this different than a case where a woman
came to grind her wheat, not to bake the bread, but to
grind the wheat, and the animal came and ate the wheat and
was damaged, and we say פטור? patur? ואם הוזקה חייבת, Ve'im huzkah
chayaves, but if the
animal—sorry—פטור, patur, that right, the animal is פטור patur for eating the
wheat, and if the animal was damaged, חייבת, chayaves, she has to
pay for damage to the animal. So טעמא שלא ברשות. Ta'ama shelo
berishus. That was because there was without permission. הא ברשות birshut, פטור
patur, *ha birshut patur* and maybe we should say if she came
with permission then she should be פטור patur, *patur* for the damage
caused to the animal and what's the difference? אמרי לטחון חטין *amri
litchon chitin* כיון דלא בעיא צניעותא *keivan dela ba'ei tzniuta* מידי לא
בעיא מסלקי מרוותא דחצר נפשייהו *midi lo ba'ei mesalkei marvata dechatzer nafshaihu*
because grinding wheat does not require a level of a higher level
of צניעות tzniut. *tzniut*, the homeowner will still be around while she's
guarding while she's grinding the wheat, and therefore the homeowner is still
responsible for the animal. But in the case of
baking, homeowner's not responsible for the animal.
No, שלא ברשות shelo birshut, *shelo birshut* she came without permission. And
then the animal came and got damaged, so she would be פטורה
pturah. *petura* in the case where it was הא ברשות birshut פטור
patur. *ha birshut patur*. If it was with permission, she comes to
grind her wheat and she got permission of the homeowner, and the
homeowner is still around because she doesn't need any level of צניעות
*tzniut* for grinding wheat. Then the goat came and ate the wheat
and died, she will be פטורה *petura* because the homeowner should have
guarded the goat.
And if the goat just ate it and didn't die, the homeowner
would be חייב chayav *chayav* for the wheat.
Correct. And in the case where she was coming to bake the
dough, because baking bread requires a higher level of צניעות *tzniut*.
As you're rolling up your, let's see.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, we're going to see in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says, so מרוותא דחצר מסלקי נפשייהו *marvata dechatzer
mesalkei nafshaihu* אבל אדידיה רמיא נטירותא *aval adidei ramia netiruta*. Okay, so
Ravina's true, so in that case when when she came and she
accepted the שמירה shmira *shmira*. אבל אפיה כיון דבעיא היא צניעותא *aval
afeia keivan deba'ei hi tzniuta* so מרוותא דחצר מסלקי נפשייהו *marvata dechatzer
mesalkei nafshaihu*. Since baking bread requires a higher level of צניעות *tzniut*,
the homeowner will say, okay, I'm going to come back in an
hour. הכא לדידה רמיא נטירותא *hacha ledida ramia netiruta*. And therefore she
accepted it on herself the responsibility to watch out for the animal.
If you look in רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, so רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says,
לאפות בעיא צניעותא *le'efot ba'ei tzniuta*. What what higher level of צניעות
*tzniut* do you need for baking? As Michael noted, שמגלה זרועותיה *shemegaleh
zero'oteiha*. She rolls up her sleeves when she's kneading the dough because
she doesn't want to get her shirt sleeves dirty. The question is
how far up do you roll your sleeves to be a compromising
level of צניעות *tzniut*? That's an interesting question. It's unclear from the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. The point is that grinding wheat you don't change
the way you're dressed in any way, so there's no problem of
צניעות *tzniut*. But to bake bread, where you would need to roll
up your sleeves in some way, there could be, or it was
presumably very common, that the women would not do that while the
men were around.
Okay, so wait, so in that case then what's the law again?
So in that case then, it must be that for the case
of baking where she has she's come with permission and the owner
knows homeowner knows she's there, so the homeowner will know that she
wants privacy so he'll leave. It must be then that she has
accepted upon herself responsibility for the animals while the homeowner is gone.
And therefore if the goat came and ate the dough and died,
it's her fault. It's not the goat's fault.
But if the goat didn't die, just ate the dough,
then everyone is פטור patur.
*patur*. Oh no, he wouldn't be חייב chayav.
*chayav*. Correct. For the dough. No, he's not חייב chayav *chayav* for
the dough. Because again, it's her fault, she should have guarded the
goat from eating the dough.
And she came שלא ברשות shelo birshut *shelo birshut* to bake?
If she came שלא ברשות shelo b'reshut? *shelo birshut*, but there's no
difference between baking and not baking if it was שלא ברשות birshut,
*shelo birshut*. The point the difference between baking and grinding is that
the homeowner knew. In the case of grinding he would still be
there, so he's responsible for the animal, but in the case of
baking he would have left, so she becomes responsible for the animal.
So if she were baking or grinding without רשות reshut, *reshut*? That's
what I was gonna ask. And the animal died, she did not
accept upon herself any obligation
then she's פטורה *petura*.
So it's a strange thing though. It is very strange. The elephant
in the room is she's it never would have happened if she
hadn't broken into the house to decide to do but again, what
happened?
The animal should have known not to overeat to the point of
death.
So the only assumption here is that the animal is a בר
דעת *bar daat* on some level?
The animal has a certain amount of animal instinct, we've seen that
throughout the מסכת *masechet*. Right, that animals can be expected to have
a certain threshold I mean that's the difference between a שור shor
*shor* and a בור bor *bor*, or שור shor... *shor* and אש
*esh* really. אש *esh* besides רוח אחרת *ruach acheret* whatever it is.
I'm forgetting the exact לשון הגמרא *lashon hagemara*. Not רוח מצויה *ruach
metzuya* but that the כח אחרת מעורב בו *koach acheret me'urav bo*.
That אש *esh* fine whatever about that, but that אש *esh* is
not alive. An animal is alive and an animal has a certain
amount of, you can't say דעת *daat*, but a certain amount of
awareness or a certain amount of knowledge, like we say the question
of whether you have כוונה להזיק kavana le-hazik *kavana lehazik* or not.
Well an animal can have כוונה להזיק kavana le-hazik, *kavana lehazik* or
not, that's the difference between קרן keren, *keren* and שן shein, *shen*,
right? So an animal can have intent, an animal can have a
will, so an animal should know not to eat too much. Okay
now again, some animals are maybe not so smart.
רב Rav משרשיא *Rav Mesharshiya*, didn't we say ואם
הוזקה חייבת chayavet *ve'im huzka chayavet*? ואם הוזקה חייבת *ve'im huzka chayavet*
in the case, sorry going back, טעמא דשלא ברשות birshut?
*taama deshlo birshut*. מהא דחייביה רבא Rava. לשלומי דמי ברחא *maha dechayvei
Rava leshalumei
demei barcha*.
Right. No, but that לימא פליגי *leima pligi*.
No, but מאי שנא אשה שנכנסה לטחון חטין אצל בעל הבית ba'al
habayit שלא ברשות birshut, ואכלתן בהמתו של בעל הבית ba'al habayit, פטור
patur.
ואם הוזקה חייב chayav *mai shena isha shenichnesa litchon chitin etzel ba'al
habayit shelo birshut ve'achaltan behemto shel ba'al habayit patur ve'im huzka chayav*
טעמא דשלא ברשות *taama deshlo birshut*.
No, so פטור patur. *patur*. The owner of the goat for eating
the animal, the thing, ואם הוזקה חייבת. If חייב chayav though, if
פשיטא שלא ברשות.
pshita shelo birshut. Okay fine. No, so you'll say no. But that's
because it was with the baking. That is, if it was ברשות,
it means you accepted שמירה shmira on yourself because of the צניעות.
The normal case is grinding the wheat and whether it's ברשות or
לא ברשות. lo birshut. The baking adds an extra layer, which is
that she accepted upon herself שמירה shmira of the animal and that's
the difference. That's why it gets confusing because the normal case, the
grinding the wheat, ברשות, and the animal comes and eats the wheat,
פטורה. The fact that makes her חייבת is because when she comes
to bake, she wants privacy so she takes upon herself the שמירה
shmira. of the animal. Now you should again ask, why does the
owner not bring the goat with him? But that's a... Okay. הכניס
שורו לחצר בעל הבית. Hichnis shoro lachatzer ba'al habayit. Okay, you brought
your animal into someone else's property. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, we're
going to have three cases from Rava, each one kind of going
into some of the details about בור bor. and we're going to
see. אמר רבא הכניס שורו לחצר בעל הבית, Amar Rava hichnis shoro
lachatzer ba'al habayit, you brought your animal into someone else's property, שלא
ברשות, without permission, וחפר בה בורות שיחין ומערות, vechafar bah borot schichin
ume'arot, and then the animal dug some holes. I got a question
about this a few weeks ago and I was not yet familiar
with this גמרא Gemara and I answered it I think incorrectly so
I'm glad I got to learn this now. So the animal came
and dug some holes in someone else's property. בעל השור חייב בנזקי
חצר. Ba'al hashor chayav binzkei chatzer. The owner of the animal has
to pay for the repair to the field or to the ground.
That makes sense. ובעל חצר חייב בנזקי הבור. Uba'al chatzer chayav binzkei
habor. But and now we have to read the ראב"ד Ravad on
this but we'll have to see. So the בעל החצר, ba'al hachatzer,
the owner of the property
becomes liable for damage caused by the בור. bor, That is, once
the animal has created the בור, bor. the owner of the property
becomes חייב. chayav So you'll say how does that happen? So the
ראב"ד Ravad has a very sharp explanation. The ראב"ד Ravad says like
this: The ראב"ד Ravad says the whole way it works is because
you were initially חייב chayav for נזקי השור, nizkei hashor, that is
the animal dug the holes. Why, the ראב"ד Ravad says, דבעל השור
שילם ליה לבעל חצר נזקי החפירה, deba'al hashor shalem lei leba'al chatzer
nizkei hachafira, once the owner of the animal has paid for the
damage to the ground for digging the holes, וכמאן דמליא דמי, ukman
demalya dami, from his perspective it's like he already filled them in.
That is, he paid for the damage and now it becomes the
responsibility of the owner of the property. That is, once he's paid
back, it makes sense to say now it's his responsibility. ובעל חצר
דשבקיה ולא מליה הוי ליה כאילו חפירה איהו מחייב. uba'al chatzer deshavkei
velo malya havei lei ke'ilu chafira ihu mechayev. It's like he... You
already paid. Only once he paid it sounds like from the ראב"ד.
Ravad.
Because רש"י Rashi says that he's
הפקר.
hefker.
Right. Or the question of הפקר hefker becomes important for בור. bor
Right? We have מחלוקת machloket between רב ושמואל Rav uShmuel about whether
or not a בור bor. can function as a... To make you
חייב Chayav. unless you made it הפקר hefker or not. Because if
you dug the hole well maybe it's your property so you shouldn't
be חייב chayav, anyway. Okay. So we're going to have to see.
אמר רבא הכניס שורו לחצר בעל הבית שלא ברשות וחפר בה בורות
שיחין ומערות. Amar Rava hichnis shoro lachatzer ba'al habayit shelo birshut vechafar
bah borot schichin ume'arot. Okay. So why? So בעל חצר חייב בנזקי
הבור, ba'al chatzer chayav binzkei habor, אף על גב דאמר מר, af
al gav de'amar mar, even though
we have a דרשה, drasha, כי יכרה איש בור ולא שור בור.
ki yichreh ish bor velo shor bor.
It's only if a person digs the hole but not if an
animal digs the hole. Because if an animal digs the hole it
would be some kind of גרמא grama or it's too far removed.
You can't claim responsibility for that. But the point is that in
this case because it was in someone else's property and you already
paid or perhaps already were even liable to pay, there's some transfer
of ownership there of the holes that makes the property owner responsible
for the holes. Let's see. Okay. כיון דאית ליה למלויי ולא מליה
כמאן דכריה דמי. Keivan de'it lei lemalyai velo malya kman decharyei dami.
The fact that he should have filled them in and did not
fill it in,
it's like he dug it himself.
Okay.
Is it for future damages?
For future damages caused by the בור. bor That is, if something
came and someone else came and fell in the בור bor. and
was injured, then the owner of the חצר chatzer will be liable.
Damages within that...
Well
right, now well nothing happened yet.
But this is parallel to the תחינת חיטין techinat chitin case above.
In other words, I brought my שור shor into your property שלא
ברשות and these בורות borot are still there and they were paid
for, they already... He paid you, the guy whose שור... shor So
they're your בורות. borot. My שור shor, is now in your property
without permission.
Or even the שור shor. has left already. Now there are בורות
borot in your property.
I understand, but in other words I'm there without permission. Right. You're
still חייב chayav. if you're the בעל החצר. ba'al hachatzer.
The בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer is חייב chayav? according to the ראב"ד
Ravad because at that point he already assumed responsibility for it, perhaps
not, perhaps even just at the point where he's left them around
long enough that he should have filled them in and did not
yet fill them in, it's as if he dug them himself. If
you look in רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi, actually gives a very nice
explanation. There's a long
רש"י, the upcoming רש"י in the next case is going to fill
us in a little bit about some of the details about בור.
bor, Sorry about the pun.
Okay. כמאן דכריה דמי. Kman decharyei dami. also to note,
יעקב Yaakov says to יוסף Yosef about the the grave that he
dug in מערת המכפלה Ma'arat Hamachpelah אשר כריתי לי, Asher kariti li,
right? The מפרשים Meforshim there have a big מחלוקת machlokeit about what
does that actually mean, but obviously from the Aramaic cognate, it sounds
like pretty obviously he's to dig the hole, to dig the grave.
Okay.
The sense of כירה kirah and מכירה. mechirah.
Okay, of course, but we have we have other things to deal
with, at least על דרך הפשט. al derech hapeshat. ואמר רבא: V'amar
Rava: הכניס שורו לחצר בעל הבית שלא ברשות. Hichnis shoro l'chatzer ba'al
habayit shelo b'reshut. You brought your animal into someone else's property without
permission. והזיק את בעל הבית, Vehizik et ba'al habayit, and the animal
damaged the property owner, או בעל הבית הוזק בו, o ba'al habayit
huzak bo, or he got damaged passively by the animal, like he
tripped over it while it was asleep or something. חייב. chayav
So he's חייב, chayav that is, it's your fault, why was your
animal doing in this person's property? So רבצת פטור. Ravtzat patur. Now
it sounds like רבצת ravtzat means sitting down. The animal sat down,
then you should be פטור, patur but that doesn't make any sense.
ומשום דרבצת פטור? Umishum d'ravtzat patur? The fact that the animal sat
down makes you פטור, patur even though it was שלא ברשות? אמר
רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: מאי רבצת? Mai ravtzat? שהרביץ גללים Sheherbitz
glalim ונטנפו כליו של בעל הבית. venitnefu kelav shel ba'al habayit. No,
it means that
the animal defecated in the property, and the property owner's clothing or
כלים keilim got dirtied by that, got soiled from that. דהוו גללים
בור, Dehavu glalim bor, because the waste is considered to be בור,
bor it's a stationary
property נזק, nezek, ולא מצינו בור שחייב בו את הכלים, v'lo matzinu
bor shechayav bo et hakeilim, because there's a special exemption of כלים
keilim from בור bor, and therefore tough nuggies. The the issue is
that the animal did not directly cause any damage. The animal created
a בור, bor similar to our animal dug the בור bor problem,
but here the only damage was to the כלים, keilim, and if
the damage is to כלים, keilim, בור bor, is פטור. patur If
you look in the long רש״י, Rashi, long רש״י Rashi ונטנפו כליו,
venitnefu kelav, רש״י Rashi there explains a little bit about the previous
cases, it says, וכגון דנפלה גמלו ולא העמידה מחייבינן לה משום בור.
U'kegon denafela gamlo v'lo he'emida mechayvinan leh mishum bor. If your camel
fell over and you did not upright the animal quickly, then it's
considered to be בור, bor. ואף על גב דאיהו לא כרה, v'af
al gav d'ihu lo karah, even though you didn't dig the hole,
as it were, אלא הגמל כרהו, ela hagamal k'rahu, כיוון דבשעת נפילה
דידהו הוא, keivan d'bishat nefilah didehu hu, the fact is that at
the time the animal fell over, or the fact that the waste
fell out of the animal, it belonged to you,
ועליה לסלוקי, v'alei lesalukei, and it was your responsibility to remove it,
כמו דכריה איהו דמי. kemo d'karaya ihu dami. It's like it belongs
to, it's your responsibility. That is, רש״י Rashi says two criteria: number
one, it belonged to you at the time the damage was created;
and number two, it was your responsibility to resolve that issue, to
clean it up, to upright the animal, to fix the problem. Okay.
Do we realize why it's not like צרורות? tzrorot? Is it because
the גללים glalim are somehow not his or because רש״י Rashi says...
Ah, so we're going to get to that. That's in the גמרא
Gemara. coming up. ולא מצינו בור שחייב בו את הכלים. V'lo matzinu
bor shechayav bo et hakeilim. הניחא לשמואל, Hani-cha l'Shmuel, fine, this all
makes sense according to שמואל, Shmuel, why? דאמר כל תקלה בור הוא,
d'amar kol takalah bor hu, because שמואל Shmuel said any תקלה, takalah,
right? Any stationary תקלה takalah is considered to be בור. bor. אלא
לרב דאמר עד דמפקר ליה, Ela l'Rav d'amar ad d'mafkar leh, רב
Rav says it has to be הפקר hefker in order to count
as בור. bor, Okay, so מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? אמרי
סתם גללים אפקורי מפקר להו. Amrei stam glalim afkorei mafkar lehu. No,
most animal waste is considered to be הפקר hefker at the point
where it comes out of the animal. There's obviously a lot of
נפקא מינה nafka mina regarding this for pooper scooper laws and things
like that and in terms of
public care for animal waste, you know, from dogs especially. So it's
important to consider that there. So that's the part of the difference
on צרורות tzrorot we say is by רגל. regel. It's a little
bit different. We saw that the animal gets a הנאה hana'ah from
relieving itself, so it's more like שן, shen so we don't have
צרורות tzrorot in the same way. That was, came up relatively early
in the מסכתא, masechta, but it was a מחלוקת machlokeit between רש״י
Rashi and רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel about that. I forget exactly the
details. Okay.
Question? Since it's the case earlier where there was an issue about
someone got benefit from an animal defecating because it was great fertilizer?
No,
I don't remember fertilizer, but I'm remembering that the animal
got benefit from relieving itself.
Well, and there was fertilizer that was left in the middle of
the road and the question of whether, whether, you know, as people
like to come and pick it up and stuff like that.
Right, who owns it at what point. Okay. So we have now
a third case from רבא. Rava. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: נכנס לחצר
בעל הבית שלא ברשות, Nichnas l'chatzer ba'al habayit shelo b'reshut, a person
entered into someone else's property. Now this is about אדם המזיק, adam
hamazik, now we're not talking about שור, shor. a person went into
someone else's property without permission, והזיק את בעל הבית, vehizik et ba'al
habayit, and damaged the owner, או בעל הבית הוזק בו, o ba'al
habayit huzak bo, or the owner was damaged, either tripped over him,
something like that, חייב. chayav הזיקו בעל הבית פטור, Heziko ba'al habayit
patur, but if the בעל הבית damaged the person who came in,
then he's פטור. patur. So we have to see. So who's חייב?
chayav We would think the person who entered without permission is חייב
chayav for the any damage to the בעל הבית, and if the
property owner
hurt this person, he should be פטור. patur. So that seems strange.
אמר רב פפא Rav Pappa *Amar Rav Papa*, לא אמרן אלא דלא
הוה ידע ביה *Lo amrun ela d'lo hava yada bei*. It's only
if he didn't know he was there.
Is that close to a בבא דמחתרת *Bava
d'machteret*, you know, in a way? Something like that, which is
not the same
but, well, we know אדם מועד mu'ad לעולם *Adam Muad L'olam*. That
is, if I trip over you or kick you by accident while
you're asleep in my yard, I should be פטור patur. *Patur*? So
it must be דלא הוה ידע ביה *d'lo hava yada bei*. And
this goes back to the מחלוקת machloket *Machloket* between Ramban and Tosafot
we saw earlier that in a case of אונס גמור *Ones Gamur*,
you didn't have any knowledge that this person was there at all.
So in a case of אונס גמור *Ones Gamur*, Ramban thinks you're
still חייב chayav *Chayav* and Tosafot thinks you're פטור patur. *Patur*. So
this is an interesting proof for the position of Tosafot because דלא
הוה ידע ביה *d'lo hava yada bei*, the fact that you didn't
know about it, Rav Papa says so that's what makes you פטור
patur. *Patur*. אבל הוה ידע ביה *Aval hava yada bei*, if you
knew that the person was there, הזיקו בעל הבית חייב chayav *Heiziko
Baal Habayit Chayav*. If the בעל הבית *Baal Habayit* damages this trespasser,
he's still חייב chayav, *Chayav*. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama? *Mai Taama*? משום
דאמר ליה *Mishum d'amar lei*, ניהי דאית לך רשותא לאפוקי *Nihi d'it
lach reshu l'afukei*, you have permission to remove me from your property,
לאזוקי לית לך רשותא *l'azukei leit lach reshu*, you don't have any
permission to damage me. That is the only way you have an
obligation, even someone who's, and this is different than בבא דמחתרת *Bava
d'machteret*. בבא דמחתרת *Bava d'machteret* we'll have to see in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*,
case of someone who is tunneling into your property for nefarious purposes,
to come steal from you, perhaps even with willing to kill you.
And in this case, you
have permission to make that assumption. Correct.
In this case, this is just a person סתם stam *Stam* trespassing,
someone who came to sleep in my front yard, someone who came
to use my barbecue without permission. He's not stealing, he's not with
any violent intent. And in this case, so he says, you have
permission to remove me from your property, you don't have permission to
damage me, to injure me. What that means is you actually have
responsibility for a non-violent solution to the problem, which is very interesting.
That is you can't resort to violence to remove this person from
your property. You have to go to something that's not going to
or if you do you're חייב chayav *Chayav* to pay the damage.
Exactly. How do you know? And that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* deals exactly with that case, which is when is a
case of בבא דמחתרת *Bava d'machteret* considered to be a capital case
or not. So we say, the פסוק *Pasuk* says, אם זרחה השמש
עליו *Im zaracha hashemesh alav*, if the sun shines on him, so
we understand that to mean if it's a case where it's clear
to you, so clear that he's not coming with dangerous intent, then
you don't have permission
to injure him or to kill him. But if it's a case
where even if you're unsure, so בא להורגך השכם להורגו *ba l'hargecha
hashkem l'hargo*, someone's coming to kill you you have to defend yourself
first as the רודף *Rodef*. So there's some interesting, I mean that's
a whole fun סוגיא sugya *Sugya*, but that's coming up in already...
happens in a lot of ways. It could be accidental or the
animal just wandered onto the property or something, just got lost or
something.
Well, this is a person, person got lost. Right, I wandered into
somebody else's field, right.
Doesn't have to be intentional. Exactly.
Exactly.
Right, but it's an interesting thing of like where do we whose
rights we favor of like I don't know if it's accidental or
not, right? And like maybe it was intentional.
It's also just interesting to note, we have this is now the
third מימרא *Memra* of Rava that we've seen. The second and third
each have had a qualifying statement by Rav Papa. Rav Papa clarified
the statement about רבץ *Ravatz*. רבץ *Ravatz* doesn't mean to be sitting
down, it meant a case where the animal had made waste in
the person's property. And here, Rav Papa is coming to clarify the
difference between הוה ידע ביה *Hava yada bei* and לא הוה ידע
ביה *Lo hava yada bei*. Okay. דאזלו לטעמייהו *D'azu l'taameihu*, it fits
their normal reasoning, דאמר רבא ואיתימא רב פפא Rav Pappa *d'amar Rava
v'itayma Rav Papa*, or it fits either what Rava said or perhaps
what Rav Papa said, שניהם ברשות או שניהם שלא ברשות *Shneihem b'reshut
o shneihem shelo b'reshut*, if two people are there either with permission
or without permission, that is two people are in רשות הרבים *Reshut
Harabim* or two people are in a חצר chatzer השותפין *Chatzer Hashutafim*
that they're both joint owners of, or two people are both trespassing
in somebody else's property without permission, הזיקו זה את זה חייבין *Heiziko
zeh et zeh chayavin*, if they damage each other then they're obligated
to pay. הוזקו זה בזה פטורין *Huzku zeh bazeh pturin*, and if
they accidentally get damaged then they're פטור patur. *Patur*, so they're each
פטור *Patur*. טעם דשניהם ברשות או שניהם שלא ברשות *Taama d'shneihem b'reshut
o shneihem shelo b'reshut*, they're only equivalent since they both have the
same rights regarding the property, that is they were either both allowed
to be there or both not allowed to be there. אבל אחד
ברשות ואחד שלא ברשות *Aval echad b'reshut v'echad shelo b'reshut*, if one
was there with permission and one not, that is one is the
owner and one is trespassing or something like that, דברשות פטור *d'b'reshut
patur*, the one who has permission will be פטור *Patur*, שלא ברשות
חייב chayav *shelo b'reshut chayav*, with the qualifier of course, פטור *Patur*
only if he did not know that the other person was there
according to Rav Papa because that's what makes it אונס גמור *Ones
Gamur*, otherwise we still have to say אדם מועד mu'ad לעולם *Adam
Muad L'olam*. Okay. נפל לבור והבאיש מימיו חייב chayav *Nafal labor v'hivish
memav chayav*. If an animal fell into a בור bor, *Bor* and
then the water got spoiled, the water now has a dead animal
in it, so then the owner of the animal is חייב chayav
*Chayav* for the damage caused to the water. That was in our
Mishna. אמר רבא Amar Rava: *Amar Rava*, לא שנו אלא שהבאיש בשעת
נפילה *lo shanu ela shehivish b'shaat nefila*, it only makes sense to
say this if the water became spoiled at the time that the
animal fell into the well, אבל לאחר נפילה פטור *aval l'achar nefila
patur*. But after the animal fell in, that is, and the animal
carcass starts to rot over several weeks, then you'll be פטור. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? הוי שור בור, Havai shor bor, the dead animal
has become a בור, bor a stationary היזק, hezek, the מים mayim
כלים, kelim, and the water is considered to be כלים. kelim. Interestingly
enough, it's considered כלים. kelim. It is weird.
I thought that to myself as you...
If we remember the תוספות Tosafot in the first פרק, perek, תוספות
Tosafot says that food, there's at least some kind of a מחלוקת
about how does food get qualified. Is food like the animal? It
was an animal schlepping a load of food that fell into a
בור, bor, so is the food that was damaged considered to be
כלים kelim or is the food considered to be part of the
animal because it's more like it's edible or it's movable or something?
So that's part of the question here, but here מים mayim is
considered to be כלים. kelim. רש"י says כל חפצים ככלים kol chafatzim
k'kelim דלא חייב בבור. d'lo chayav b'bor. Any objects are considered to
be כלים, kelim, that is, not animals and not people. Anything else
is כלים kelim according to רש"י, ומצינו בור שחייב בו את הכלים
u'matzinu bor shechayav bo et hakelim because the בור bor has damaged
כלים, kelim, that is, the dead cow rotting in the well over
time, which is stationary, which is בור, bor. has damaged כלים, kelim,
that's פטור. Okay.
I'm sorry, I don't remember what the reasoning for that is.
It's a גזירת הכתוב, gezerat hakatuv, yeah.
That גזירת
הכתוב gezerat
hakatuv means it doesn't have reasoning. It's just how it is. That's
the rule. And that's part of... this is another answer to the
question of when we said, we saw that
complicated גמרא Gemara a few... what, a week and a half ago,
about when the Romans came, more than a week and a half
ago, the Romans came and they learned נזיקין Nezikin and they were
troubled by the fact that non-Jews don't have the same standing in
הלכה halacha as Jews regarding נזיקין. Nezikin. But in fact it makes
a lot of sense, which is to say there are the logical
parts of נזיקין Nezikin which are very reasonable, and then there are
all sorts of strange exceptions and strange loopholes and all kinds of
things. The fact that a בור bor will be פטור for כלים
kelim is a special thing from the תורה. Torah. Why should that
apply to non-Jews? That doesn't make any sense. That's something from us
that we got from God. It's not logical or intrinsic to the
system.
But if we're talking about the ox rotting in the well, wouldn't
the trespasser be responsible to have taken it out before it rots?
I don't know.
Maybe it's too hard.
Well, the
fact that he's חייב chayav for the damage means that it was
his responsibility to have to remove it. But meaning he doesn't have
to remove it, it's just whatever damage it causes while it's there,
he's going to be חייב to pay for.
But we're saying once it's rotting, he's not responsible because it's... you
have this other...
Well, he's not חייב because of a special exemption. You could then
you get into the question, does פטור really mean he's totally off
the hook or does it mean he's פטור מדיני אדם mi-dinei adam
but he has an ethical responsibility?
But at least shouldn't he be responsible to take it out before
it rots?
That's a very good question, but it sounds like not. Sounds like
he has no real responsibility.
Getting a 2,000 pound
ox
out of a well, right,
is not trivial.
For sure. Especially, I mean even now, when you know
when Timmy fell down the well and Lassie had to go get,
you know, these are complicated issues. Okay. So הניחא לשמואל. hani cha
l'Shmuel. This is fine for שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר כל תקלה בור הוא,
d'amar kol takala bor hu, right? It's always easier for שמואל Shmuel
because שמואל Shmuel is the one who says everything is בור. bor
אלא לרב דאמר עד דמפקיר ליה, ela l'Rav d'amar ad d'mafkir lei,
but רב Rav who requires that it be הפקר, hefker, so מאי
איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? What can we say to defend רב's
Rav? position? Obviously the owner of the ox still owns the carcass,
so it's not הפקר. hefker.
Right, but if he can't get it out, wouldn't he be...
wouldn't he be מפקיר mafkir what's at the bottom of the well
that he has no way... I don't know, he says I'm going
to come back and get the bones, you know, I want the
bones. So he has not been מפקיר, mafkir, so it's still a
שור. shor, No, exactly, it's still שור. shor. And therefore he should
be חייב for כלים. kelim.
So it's still שור, even the bones. It's still שור.
But now we have a much better answer.
So shouldn't he intentionally not be מפקיר, mafkir, wouldn't we assume he's
מפקיר mafkir something at the bottom
of the well that he has no way... An ox carcass is
great for dog food, you know, until it starts to rot,
but if he can't, if he can no longer use it, it's
in...
so now you're talking about יאוש שלא מדעת. ye'ush shelo m'da'at. But
so that's interesting and is יאוש ye'ush the same as הפקר, hefker,
which are both big questions. Okay. So מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
l'meimar? So what can we say for רב? Rav, And now we
have a better answer. That's really the answer, which is that the
answer for שמואל Shmuel is overly simplistic. We want a deeper answer
and this is going to get back to a major question we
have. אלא איתמר הכי איתמר. ela itmar hachi itmar. This is how
we should say. אמר רבא: לא שנו אלא שהבאיש מגופו. lo shanu
ela shehiv'ish migufo. It's you're only חייב if the animal started to
rot from itself. אבל הבאיש מריחו, aval hiv'ish m'reicho,
but
if the water became repugnant not because of the actual substance of
the cow but from only from the smell of the cow, פטור.
מאי טעמא? גרמא בעלמא הוא. gerama b'alma hu. It's only גרמה. gerama.
דגרמה בעלמא לא מחייב. d'gerama b'alma lo mechayev. גרמה gerama in נזיקין
Nezikin we know you're פטור. You have an ethical obligation to remove
it, it's אסור, asur, but it's not... you're not חייב to pay
the damages. רמב"ן Ramban in his קונטרס דינא דגרמי Kuntres Dina d'Garmi
says I don't understand this גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara is not
גרמה, gerama, it's not fully indirect. This should be גרמי. garmi. This
should be a medium indirect case. Why? Because obviously the cow is
the one causing the smell. Fine, you're going to tell me the
smell was is one step removed because of the cow, but it
still was a totally inevitable result. So רמב"ן Ramban thinks this is
גרמי Garmi and then he says he has to answer the גמרא
why does this גמרא
conclude that גרמא Grama is a good answer? So first piece of
data he has is that the רי"ף Rif doesn't quote this סוגיא
sugya at all. So maybe this סוגיא sugya is not even להלכה.
la-halacha. That's possibility number one. Possibility number two, רמב"ן Ramban says, maybe
there's a difference between נזקי ממון nizkei mamon and אדם המזיק. adam
ha-mazik. נזקי ממון Nizkei mamon perhaps, when an animal causes damage, maybe
there is no distinction between גרמא grama and גרמי. garmi. Maybe the
distinction between גרמא grama and גרמי garmi is only by a person
causing damage, because those fine differences in indirect damage, indirect cause, are
only going to be meaningful regarding a person, but not regarding the
animal causing the damage. So it's just an interesting piece here, which
is that the גמרא seems to assert very straightforwardly that this is
a case of גרמא, grama, רמב"ן Ramban based on his definition thinks
it can't be גרמא grama and he has to explain then how
does the סוגיא make any sense?
So גרמי garmi is closer to direct... Right, exactly.
But it's still not direct direct, it's a little bit
indirect.
It's also almost like a passive context, like ריח, reiach, in other
words, like
the ריח reiach is less intrinsic to the object than the animal
itself. Right, okay. היה אביו ובנו לתוכו משלם את הכופר. Haya avivo
u-vno l-tocho m'shalem et ha-kofer. The משנה Mishnah had said if the
property owner's son or father were in the בור bor and the
animal fell on top of them in the בור bor. and killed
them, then he has to pay כופר, kofer, the owner of the
animal has to pay כופר. kofer. ואמאי הא תם הוא Ve-amai ha
tam hu? Why should you pay כופר, kofer, the animal's a תם?
tam?
Because whoever heard of an animal מועד mu'ad, for falling into holes?
Right, let's see. דאמר רב במועד ליפול על בני אדם בבורות עסקינן.
De-amar Rav be-mu'ad lippol al benei adam bi-vurot askinan. No, we must
be talking about a case of a מועד mu'ad animal that was
for this very rare case, that is multiple times has fallen on
top of people in a well.
And survived,
gotten pulled out of the well and lived to fall on top
of people again.
The only thing I would say, just to make this a little
bit more, I think בורות borot are cisterns and not wells and
they're actually bigger...
certainly wider than what we're imagining.
Right, in other words not like the kind of well...
could be less deep, we know a בור bor could be as
shallow as ten טפחים. tefachim.
Right, so the cisterns are different...
that's certainly true.
Our
swimming pools could certainly be considered an empty dry swimming pool is
certainly a בור.
Yeah, exactly. There's a whole lot of secular law about liability for
swimming pools.
That's certainly true, so they have a lot to build on here.
Doesn't the תם tam also where fathers and sons have the habit
of hanging out?
Ah, so we're going to see, it's a מחלוקת אמוראים. machloket amora'im.
Because the women are kneading the dough and they need the... then
the men go to...
okay, so let's... the men had to leave the house, right, okay.
So we have to see. Okay, אי הכי בר קטלא הוא ee
hachi bar-ktala hu? So then
if the animal is מועד, mu'ad then the animal should be killed,
it shouldn't just be enough to pay כופר, kofer, the animal has
to be killed. אמר רב יוסף דחזא ירוקא ונפל. Amar Rav Yosef
de-chaza yeroka ve-nafal. No, the animal saw some vegetables growing at the
edge of the בור and went to munch on them and then
fell in. So it's not actual a problem of קרן, the animal
jumped into the hole in order to kill someone, but the animal
was just minding its own business eating and this is a תולדה
toladah of שן and therefore it doesn't have כוונה kavana? להזיק and
therefore the animal wouldn't be killed.
Forget מועד mu'ad for a second, so right, we're not doing מועד
mu'ad? anymore?
It still would have to be מועד mu'ad, in order to pay
כופר, kofer, but the animal then three times in a row must
have been munching the grass at the edge of the hole and
fallen in.
We're still going with מועד?
mu'ad That's how so far how we are. With כוונה? Just it
doesn't have כוונה להזיק, exactly, because that way the animal then must
not have been a בר קטלא, bar-ktala, the animal doesn't deserve to
be killed. Okay, שמואל Shmuel has a different
explanation. שמואל אמר הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא. Shmuel amar ha
manni Rabbi Yossi Ha-Glili hi. It must be רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi
Yossi Ha-Glili שיטה. shitta. What does רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi Ha-Glili
say? תם משלם חצי כופר. Tam m'shalem chatzi kofer. No, forget מועד,
obviously we're not talking about an animal that three times in a
row fell on top of people in a hole, it must have
been a תם, tam, but רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi Ha-Glili thinks
there is such a thing as חצי כופר. chatzi kofer.
First time we've seen this concept?
I don't think so, I think it came up a few times,
it was on ט"ו tet-vav and כ"ו, kaf-vav, so here you can
add מ"ח עמוד ב' mem-chet amud bet to the list. רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yossi Ha-Glili thinks there is such a thing as חצי
כופר. chatzi kofer. That is כופר, kofer, you pay full כופר kofer
when an animal kills someone, the animal is a מועד and kills
someone, and you pay חצי כופר chatzi kofer for a תם tam
animal kills someone. To a certain extent makes a lot of
sense. and how much is
חצי נזק chatzi nezek, *chatzi nezek* that
a תם tam *tam* pays just half of what the מועד *muad*
animal pays, well then so חצי כופר kofer? *chatzi kofer* as well.
But if they're very different things... Okay.
So משלם חצי כופר *meshallem chatzi kofer*.
Now עולא *Ulla* has a third approach. עולא אמר *Ulla amar* רבי
Rabbi, יוסי הגלילי היא דאמר כרבי טרפון *Rabbi Yose HaGlili hi de'amar
keRabbi Tarfon*. It must be a combination of שיטות *shitot*, it must
be רבי Rabbi, יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili* who thinks there is
such a thing as חצי כופר *chatzi kofer*, that is, a תם
tam. *tam* animal can pay some kind of כופר *kofer*, and רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon, דאמר קרן בחצר הניזק נזק שלם משלם d'amar keren
b'chatzer hanizak nezek shalem meshalem, *Rabbi Tarfon de'amar keren b'chatzer hanizak nezek
shalem meshallem* that if the קרן *keren* caused damage in חצר הניזק
chatzer hanizak. *chatzer hanizak* pays full damages for a תם *tam* animal.
Why? That is in combination רבי Rabbi יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili*
and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon* would say you pay full
כופר *kofer* if a תם *tam* animal causes a death in חצר
הניזק chatzer hanizak, *chatzer hanizak*, which is exactly the case we're talking
about, and that's why the משנה mishnah. *mishnah* did not say חצי
כופר *chatzi kofer* which would fit רבי Rebbe יוסי הגלילי שיטה shita,
*Rabbi Yose HaGlili's shita* but actually said כופר *kofer*, seemingly כופר שלם
*kofer shalem*. So you have to combine רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon. *Rabbi
Tarfon* and רבי יוסי הגלילי שיטה *Rabbi Yose HaGlili's shita*. Interestingly enough,
רבי עקיבא איגר *Rabbi Akiva Eiger* in גליון הש"ס *Gilyon HaShas* in
the very small print says, "I don't understand why it has to
be both combination of רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili* and רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon*." The way I just explained it, it
only makes sense if it's a combination of their שיטות *shitot*. So
צריך עיון *tzarich iyun*, we'll have to leave רבי עקיבא איגר *Rabbi
Akiva Eiger* for another time. So הכי נמי כופר שלם משלם *hachi
nami kofer shalem meshallem*. בשלמא לעולא *Bishlama le-Ulla*, so עולא'ס *Ulla's* position
makes sense. היינו דקתני היה אביו ובנו לתוכו *Hainu de'katani hayah aviv
u-veno letocho*. It makes sense he said that it was his father
or his son who was there, that is, the specificity of who
was in the hole who died indicates to us that it was
בחצר הניזק *be-chatzer hanizak*. The people who were there are there with
permission, are partial owners in the property to the extent that when
they're killed, according to combination רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili* and
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon*, you would pay full כופר *kofer*.
אלא לשמואל *Ela le-Shmuel*, but שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* position, which was that it
was an animal מועד *muad*—sorry, not שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* position, it's a תם
*tam* animal for falling into holes in רשות הרבים *reshut harabbim* and
we hold like רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili* who says a
תם *tam* animal pays חצי כופר *chatzi kofer*. So שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*,
מאי איריא אביו ובנו *mai irya aviv u-veno*? So then what why
do you have to specify that it's the father or the son
of the owner? אפילו אחד אחר נמי *Afilu echad acher nami*. It
could just be anybody. אחד אחר נמי *Echad acher nami*. It could
be just be anybody else. אורחא דמילתא קתני *Orcha de'milta katani*. No,
it's just the normal way of saying, that is, it's talking about
a case that was possible, which is who would be in somebody's
hole? Oh, it must have been someone related to the owner of
the hole. And not that that has any legal significance according to
שמואל *Shmuel*. So עולא *Ulla* is making a עולא *Ulla* is forced
into his extremely דחוק *dachuk* position, that is, it's based on a
combination of two minority שיטות *shitot*,
that is, neither of which we hold by and which we don't
necessarily have any precedent for knowing that they work together. So עולא
*Ulla* has to explain this משנה *mishnah* according to a rejected שיטה
*shita* combined with another rejected שיטה *shita* which we never saw that
they were combined before. So עולא'ס *Ulla's* position is very difficult to
explain the משנה *mishnah*. שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* position makes more sense, but then
you have a dangling clause in the משנה *mishnah*, why does it
say אביו ובנו *aviv u-veno*? So he says, "Okay, that's like the
way it was, it doesn't there's no reason, it doesn't have to
say that." Okay. Next. ואם הכניס ברשות בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer חייב
*Ve-im hichnis bi-reshut ba'al ha-chatzer chayav*. The משנה *mishnah* had ended off
with a line that sort of seemed to be a little bit
dangling if you remember, turning back a little bit just to see
the משנה *mishnah*. So the משנה *mishnah* had said... Okay.
That
that if you brought the animal in or if you entered in
with permission of the בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer *ba'al ha-chatzer*, you're חייב
*chayav*. So who is חייב *chayav*? And we have to see. איתמר
*Itmar*. רב Rav אמר הלכתא כתנא קמא *Rav amar hilcheta ke-Tanna Kamma*,
because we saw there was a מחלוקת *machloket* between תנא tanna קמא
*Tanna Kamma* and רבי *Rebbi*. Sorry, I want to see the משנה
*mishnah*, the length of the משנה *mishnah*. The משנה *mishnah* is on
מ"ז ע"א *Mem-Zayin Amud Alef*. The משנה *mishnah* said, "So הכניס שורו
לחצר בעל הבית שלא ברשות *hichnis shoro
le-chatzer ba'al ha-bayit she-lo bi-reshut*... Okay, but it's right at the end.
ואם הכניס ברשות בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer. חייב *Ve-im hichnis bi-reshut ba'al
ha-chatzer chayav*. If you came in with permission of the owner of
the property, you're חייב *chayav*." רבי אומר בכולן אינו חייב עד שיקבל
עליו לשמור *Rebbi omer bekulan eino chayav ad she-yekabbel alav lishmor*. The
property owner is only חייב *chayav* if he accepted responsibility to watch
over the property, that is, he only if he became a שומר
shomer. *shomer*. If he didn't become a שומר *shomer*, it's not his
responsibility. So איתמר רב אמר הלכתא כתנא קמא *itmar Rav amar hilcheta
ke-Tanna Kamma*. רב *Rav* thinks the הלכה *halacha* is like תנא קמא
*Tanna Kamma*, that you're חייב *chayav* as soon as you brought it
in ברשות *bi-reshut*, the owner has accepted some liability for your property.
Okay. שמואל אמר הלכתא כרבי *Shmuel amar hilcheta ke-Rebbi*. שמואל *Shmuel* thinks
the הלכה *halacha* is like רבי *Rebbi*, that it's only if he
actually accepted to be a שומר *shomer*, it's not not סתם stam,
*stam*. תנו רבנן Rabbanan, *Tanu rabbanan*. כנוס שורך ושמרו *Kenos shorecha u-shemoro*,
הזיק חייב הוזק פטור *hizik chayav huzak patur*. A little bit cryptic.
He said, "Bring in your ox, ושמרו *u-shemoro*, and he watched it."
So הזיק חייב *hizik chayav*, if it caused damage, then he is
חייב *chayav*, the property owner, because he accepted upon himself to
be... הוזק פטור, then it's not the owner of the animal's responsibility
because the property owner had accepted responsibility. כנוס שורך ואני אשמרנו, kenos
shorkha v'ani ashmerenu, but if he had said, bring in your animal
and I will watch it, הוזק חייב, huzak chayav, if he got
damaged then he is חייב, הזיק פטור, hezik patur, and if it
caused damage then פטור. That is the other way, that is the
owner of the animal is no longer liable because the property owner
has accepted property. So הא גופא קשיא, ha gufa kashya, so doesn't
is this a קשיא kashya on שמואל's position who said it should
follow like, sorry, it's a קשיא kashya on רב, because רב said
even סתם stam you've accepted upon yourself the שמירה. shmira, So אמר
כנוס שורך ושמרו הזיק חייב הוזק פטור, amar kenos shorkha v'shamro hezik
chayav huzak patur, טעמא דאמר ליה שמרו, tama d'amar lei shamro, because
he said to
him, watch the animal, דחייב בעל השור ופטור בעל החצר, d'chayav ba'al
hashor u'patur ba'al hachatzer, because there was no agreement on the part
of the בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer to the request of the בעל
השור, ba'al hashor, so the בעל השור ba'al hashor is still חייב
and the בעל החצר ba'al hachatzer is פטור. הא סתמא, ha stama,
but if it was totally סתם, stam that is he had never
even made the request and certainly never agreed to it, חייב בעל
החצר ופטור בעל השור, chayav ba'al hachatzer u'patur ba'al hashor, and you're
going to tell me that in a case of סתם stam then
the fact that he never even made the request that that should
be even more liable for him? דבסתם מקבל עליה נטירותא, d'bistam mekabel
alei netiruta, because in a סתם stam case he's accepted upon himself
to watch over the animal. So אימא סיפא, eima seifa, so then
how do you fit that with the סיפא? seifa? Because the סיפא
seifa said, כנוס שורך ואני אשמרנו, kenos shorkha v'ani ashmerenu, I will
watch it. So if you're saying I will watch it, הוזק חייב
הזיק פטור. huzak chayav hezik patur. טעמא דאמר ליה ואני אשמרנו, tama
d'amar lei v'ani ashmerenu, the whole reason is because he said I
will watch it, הוא דמיחייב בעל החצר ופטור בעל השור, hu d'michayev
ba'al hachatzer u'patur ba'al hashor, that's the reason why the property owner
becomes חייב and the owner of the animal becomes פטור. הא סתמא
חייב בעל השור ופטור בעל החצר, ha stama chayav ba'al hashor u'patur
ba'al hachatzer, but otherwise if he hadn't said anything then you should
say the opposite that the animal's owner should be חייב and the
property owner should be פטור. דבסתם לא מקבל עליה נטירותא, d'bistam lo
mekabel alei netiruta, because in a סתם stam case he never accepted
upon himself to be שומר. So we have to say הא תני
לדרבי ha tani l'Rabbi דאמר עד שיקבל עליו נטירותא בעל הבית לשמור,
d'amar ad sheyekabel alav netiruta ba'al habayit lishmor, and רישא רבנן סיפא
רבי. reisha rabbanan seifa Rabbi. It must be the beginning part fits
like רבנן, Rabbanan, that is even סתם stam you do accept upon
yourself
the שמירה, shmira. and the סיפא seifa is according to רבי, and
that is even though they fit very nicely, it probably has to
have interpolated in the middle the first part the רישא reisha clause
says דברי חכמים divrei chachamim and then ואמר רבי v'amar Rabbi the
סיפא. seifa. That's the way you have to understand it for it
to make sense. אמר רבי אלעזר תברא מי ששנה זו לא שנה
זו. amar Rabbi Elazar tavra mi sheshana zu lo shana zu. So
if it broke, that is if it went and broke something, the
animal went to break something in the person's property, so מי
ששנה זו, mi sheshana zu, that if the fact that it made
the change, that is
the רבנן, Rabbanan what?
מי ששנה זו איך יכול להיות רבנן ורבי? mi sheshana zu eich
yachol lihyot Rabbanan v'Rabbi?
Exactly. Right. How can one תנא have taught the same ברייתא? braita?
תברא מי ששנה זו לא שנה זו. tavra mi sheshana zu lo
shana zu. So רבא אמר כולה רבנן. Rava amar kula Rabbanan. We
have to understand that this ברייתא braita must entirely be the רבנן
שיטה, that is סתם you did accept upon yourself the שמירה. shmira
And then what do we say? So הוא אידי דנסיב רישא שמרו,
hu idi d'nasiv reisha shamro, the fact that the רישא reisha says,
watch, watch the animal, that he had requested, please watch the animal,
תנא סיפא ואני אשמרנו, tana seifa v'ani ashmerenu, and the סיפא seifa
had said, I will watch it. And that's the difference because שמרו
shamro is, who's speaking? The בעל השור ba'al hashor is speaking but
we don't hear the answer of the בעל החצר. baal hachatzer, And
in the סיפא, seifa, ואני אשמרנו v'ani ashmerenu is the בעל החצר
answering the בעל השור ba'al hashor saying, I will watch it. That
is he actively agreed and that's the difference, who was speaking. רב
פפא אמר כולה רבי. Rav Pappa amar kula Rabbi. רב פפא disagrees
with רבא. So רב פפא thinks the entire ברייתא braita is רבי,
וסבר לה כרבי טרפון, v'savar lah k'Rabbi Tarfon, and it must be
because רבי agrees to רבי טרפון, דאמר קרן בחצר הניזק נזק שלם
nezek shalem משלם, that
you pay נזק שלם nezek shaleim for קרן תם keren tam in
חצר chatzer הניזק. So what happened? That's why you would say that
the בעל השור ba'al hashor is חייב if there was no שמירה
shmira, and that the בעל החצר is חייב for if there was
שמירה, shmira. but that means even
full damages. הלכך אמר ליה שמרו, hilkhach amar lei shamro, that's why
he said guard it, because he was worried that his if his
animal would cause damage he would not even be paying חצי נזק,
chatzi nezek he would actually be paying full נזק nezek and he
was very worried about that even though it was a
תם animal. לא מסר ליה מקום בחצר, lo masar lei makom b'chatzer,
and he did not grant him ownership of any property in the
חצר because that's what makes it חצר הניזק, right? The owner of
the property, the animal is not owned by the same person as
the property, so according to רבי טרפון you would have to pay
full damages. והוי ליה קרן בחצר הניזק וקרן בחצר הניזק משלם נזק
שלם v'havei lei keren b'chatzer hanizak v'keren b'chatzer hanizak meshalem nezek shalem
according to רבי טרפון. So therefore, מי שהביא את שורו. mi shehevi
et shoro. animal to someone else's field, someone else's חצר and I
so he and I say, please watch this animal, I'm saying that
because you did not give me rights to the land. And therefore,
it's my animal in someone else's property, if my animal causes damage,
I'm gonna have to pay full liability and I wanted to get
out of that, so I said please watch this animal.
So רש״י Rashi says to the בעל החצר, watch my animal.
Exactly, and that's why he gets off the hook.
Is that, isn't that tantamount to רשות, it's tantamount to being there
ברשות?
Yes, for sure, but this is according to רבי who says it
doesn't work סתם if you came ברשות, you have to explicitly mention
the שמירה. Gotcha,
gotcha. Okay. מקרן
בחצר הניזק משלם נזק שלם. mekeren b'chatzer hanizak meshalem nezek shaleim.
So לא אמר
ליה שמרו, lo amar lei
shamro,
אקנויי אקני ליה מקום בחצר. aknuiei aknei lei makom b'chatzer. So why
did he have to ask him to watch the animal? Couldn't he
just say, okay, so lease me part of the property and then
it will be והוה ליה חצר השותפין v'havei lei chatzer hashutafin וקרן
בחצר השותפין אינו משלם אלא חצי נזק? v'keren b'chatzer hashutafin eino meshalem
ela chatzi nezek? And therefore, then the owner of the animal will
only pay חצי נזק chatzi nezek even according to רבי טרפון because
it will be joint ownership and that would be another solution. That's
why,
so he said אמר ליה שמרו, amar lei shamro, please watch my
animal, so he said, he said that to him אקנויי אקני ליה
מקום בחצר aknuiei aknei lei makom b'chatzer so it's as if equivalent
to asking for property rights to the land. That is he's, all
he's looking for is a way of getting out of his full
liability for the damage caused by this animal, which he knows is
a תם. So he wants to avoid רבי טרפון's נזק שלם nezek
shaleim. by either having someone watch it for him who assumes full
responsibility for it, or really what he's asking is please lease me
part of your property so that maximally I'll only pay חצי נזק
and not נזק שלם. So that's the difference and there we are
up to the next משנה. So we'll stop there.
שכוח. shkoach. Do you have a quick question? Sure. How much כופר?
I
think...